A Guide to the Papers of Harry Flood Byrd, 1932-1967
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Harry Flood Byrd 1932-1967
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9700-f
Ca. 2,000 items (8 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3.5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Harry F. Byrd, Jr. on November 25, 2000.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1932-1967, consists of about 2,000 items (8 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3.5 linear feet) and includes speech files, 1932-1965, topical files on various legislation, and personal family correspondence with his sons, Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Beverley Byrd, and Richard Byrd, particularly during World War II. Also present are letters from his mother, Eleanor Bolling (Flood) Byrd, 1939-1945, and an article about Harry F. Byrd, Sr. and his collection of political cartoons about himself.
Of particular note in the speech files are speeches by Senator Byrd about the civil rights movement, including a filibuster in opposition to the Civil Rights Bill of 1963, a speech on jury trial and civil rights and a speech in opposition to civil rights Bill procedure (see Box 5). Other subjects in the topical files include the Dept. of Justice and the Attorney-General, pre-emption, the Supreme Court, and the state of Virginia (chiefly news articles and statistics).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series: Series I, Speeches, and Series II, Correspondence and Topical Files.
Contents List
- Series I: Speeches Files of Harry F. Byrd, Sr.
  - Speeches 1932-1938 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Speeches 1939 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Speeches 1940 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Speeches 1941 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Speeches 1942 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Speeches 1943 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Speeches 1944 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Speeches 1945 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Speeches 1946 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Speeches 1947 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Speeches 1948 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Speeches 1949 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Speeches 1950 Jan-Apr (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Speeches 1950 May-Dec (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Speeches 1951 Jan-Apr (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Speeches 1951 May-Dec (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Speeches 1952 Jan-May (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Speeches 1952 Jun-Dec (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Speeches 1953 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Speeches 1954 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Speeches 1955 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Speeches 1956 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Speeches 1957 Jan-May (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Speeches 1957 Jun-Dec (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Speeches 1958 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Speeches 1959 Jan-May (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Speeches 1959 Jun-Dec (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Speeches 1960 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Speeches 1961 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Speeches 1962 Jan-Jun (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Speeches 1962 Jul-Dec (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Speeches 1963 Jan-May (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Speeches 1963 Jun-Dec (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Speeches 1964 Jan-May (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Speeches 1964 Jun-Nov (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Speeches 1965 (Folder 5:5)
  - Speeches - Filibuster in Opposition to the Civil Rights Bill of 1963 1964 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Speeches - Jury Trial and Civil Rights 1964 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Speeches - Opposition to Civil Rights Bill Procedure 1964 Apr 15 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Speeches - Last "Orchard Speech" 1965 (Box-folder 5:9)
- Series II: Correspondence and Topical Files
  - Correspondence - Letters from Beverley Byrd to his father, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1943-1944 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Correspondence - Letters from Beverley Byrd to his father, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1945, 1955 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Correspondence - Letters from Eleanor Bolling (Flood) Byrd to her son, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1939-1945 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Correspondence - Letters from Harry F. Byrd, Sr. to his son, Harry F. Byrd, Jr. 1945-1949, 1955 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Correspondence - Letters from Harry F. Byrd, Jr. to his father, Harry F. Byrd, Sr., including one letter from his uncle, Admiral Richard E. Byrd, January 14, 1944 1942-1944 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Correspondence - Letters from Harry F. Byrd, Jr. to his father, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1945 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Correspondence - Letters from Harry F. Byrd, Jr. to his father, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1946-1949 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Correspondence - Letters from Harry F. Byrd, Jr. to his father, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1953-1955 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Correspondence - Letters from Richard E. Byrd to his father, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1935-1945 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Correspondence of Harry F. Byrd, Sr. - Miscellaneous 1933-1965, n.d. (Box-folder 6:10)
    including Charles Lindbergh autograph (n.d.); Carter Glass (November 16, 1943); John Garland Pollard telegram appointing Harry F. Byrd, Sr. to the Senate (1933 Mar 1); John S. Battle (1965 Nov 18)
  - Article concerning Harry F. Byrd, Sr. - "Senator Byrd's Hobby - Collecting Cartoons of Himself" ca. 1953 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Winston Churchill - Topical File 1965 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Department of Justice and Attorney General - Press Releases 1956-1959 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Department of Justice and Attorney General - Press Releases 1960-1962 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Department of Justice and Attorney General - Press Releases 1963 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Department of Justice and Attorney General - Press Releases 1964-1965 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Miscellaneous News clippings, etc. 1919-1967 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Preemption - Topical File 1956-1958 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Preemption - Topical File 1959-1961 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Rural Electrification in Virginia - Topical File 1966 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Supreme Court - Topical File 1963-1964 (Box-folder 7:10)
  - Supreme Court - Topical File 1964-1965 (Box-folder 7:11)
  - Supreme Court - Criticism and Constitution 1950-1956 (Box-folder 7:12)
  - Supreme Court - Criticism and Constitution 1957-1958 (Box-folder 7:13)
  - Supreme Court - Criticism and Constitution 1959 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Supreme Court - Criticism and Constitution 1960-1963, n.d (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Virginia - Topical File 1959-1960 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Virginia - Topical File 1961 (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Virginia - Topical File 1964 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Virginia - Topical File 1965 (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Virginia - Topical File 1965 Oct (Box-folder 8:7)
  - Virginia - Chesapeake Bay Bridge Tunnel - Topical File 1964 (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Virginia - Yorktown Day - Topical File 1964 (Box-folder 8:9)
  - Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government - Topical File 1960 (Box-folder 8:10)
  - "Virginia's Senator Harry Byrd" on Time Cover 1962 Aug 17 (Box-folder 8:11)